(Watch on www.dramacool.club Support Admin)
(شاهد على www.dramacool.club دعم الإدارة)
[Sui]
[على]
[Xie]
[شيه]
Soldiers!
أيها الجنود!
Kill Lord Changxin with no mercy!
اقتل اللورد تشانغشين بلا رحمة!
Charge!
تكلفة!
Hyah! Hyah!
هيا! هيا!
[He]
[هو]
Lord Li!
اللورد لي!
Soldiers!
أيها الجنود!
Lord Changxin's main force has started attacking the city!
بدأت القوة الرئيسية للورد تشانغشين بمهاجمة المدينة!
Follow me
تابعني
to the rear of the Chongzhou Army
إلى مؤخرة جيش تشونغتشو
and go straight to Lord Changxin!
واذهب مباشرة إلى اللورد تشانغشين!
Yes!
نعم!
Lord Li, you're badly injured.
يا سيد لي، أنت مصاب بجروح بالغة.
Don't fight them head-on.
لا تواجههم وجهاً لوجه.
Leave it to us.
اترك الأمر لنا.
We will handle it!
سنتولى الأمر!
If my life can save more people,
إذا كان بإمكاني إنقاذ المزيد من الناس بحياتي،
then my death will be worth it.
عندها سيكون موتي ذا قيمة.
Mr. Jin.
السيد جين.
You...
أنت...
My Lord!
يا إلهي!
Lord Zhuo,
اللورد تشو،
take Lord Li to a safe place
خذ اللورد لي إلى مكان آمن
and take good care of him.
واعتني به جيداً.
As for destroying the rebels' stronghold,
أما بالنسبة لتدمير معقل المتمردين،
we will handle it.
سنتولى الأمر.
Mrs. Fan, we'll go with you!
سيدتي فان، سنذهب معكِ!
We'll go with you!
سنذهب معك!
-We'll go with you! -We'll go with you, Mrs. Fan!
- سنذهب معكِ! - سنذهب معكِ يا سيدة فان!
[Pursuit of Jade]
[السعي وراء اليشم]
[Episode 30]
[الحلقة 30]
♪ There's an unknown storm ahead ♪
♪ هناك عاصفة مجهولة في الطريق ♪
♪ After a long night ♪
♪ بعد ليلة طويلة ♪
♪ Only then did I see the light of dawn ♪
♪ عندها فقط رأيت نور الفجر ♪
♪ The stubbornness in my palms ♪
♪ العناد في راحتيّ ♪
♪ Walk a rugged path with honesty and integrity ♪
♪ اسلك طريقًا وعرًا بأمانة ونزاهة ♪
♪ Trampling along the way. In the end ♪
♪ دوسٌ على طول الطريق. في النهاية ♪
♪ It will all be worth it ♪
♪ سيكون الأمر يستحق كل هذا العناء ♪
♪ Fate, on its unstoppable path ♪
♪ القدر، في مساره الذي لا يمكن إيقافه ♪
♪ Burns away sorrow and lays the seeds of kindness ♪
♪ يمحو الحزن ويزرع بذور اللطف ♪
♪ The starlight in the dark ♪
♪ ضوء النجوم في الظلام ♪
♪ Will eventually light the way for the heart ♪
♪ سينير الطريق للقلب في النهاية ♪
♪ Fate, on its galloping path ♪
♪ القدر، في مساره المتسارع ♪
♪ Sheds all hesitation and tempers its edge ♪
♪ يتخلص من كل تردد ويخفف من حدته ♪
♪ The desire hidden in your eyes ♪
♪ الرغبة الكامنة في عينيك ♪
♪ Will one day spark the fire of love ♪
♪ هل ستشعل يوماً ما نار الحب ♪
♪ The gaze of the world is light ♪
♪ نظرة العالم نور ♪
[He]
[هو]
Why is He Jingyuan's army here?
لماذا يتواجد جيش هي جينغ يوان هنا؟
♪ With hearts united, the weak can defeat the strong ♪
♪ بقلوبٍ متحدة، يستطيع الضعيف هزيمة القوي ♪
Stop them! Don't let them disrupt our formation!
أوقفوهم! لا تدعوهم يعطلوا تشكيلنا!
♪ The world is full of ups and downs ♪
♪ العالم مليء بالتقلبات ♪
Yes! Follow me!
نعم! اتبعني!
Hyah!
هيا!
♪ Kindness can only belong to the victorious ♪
♪ اللطف لا يكون إلا للمنتصرين ♪
Hyah!
هيا!
Report from the front line!
تقرير من الخطوط الأمامية!
We have breached the city walls,
لقد اخترقت أسوار المدينة،
but casualties are heavy. We need reinforcements immediately!
لكن الخسائر فادحة. نحن بحاجة إلى تعزيزات فورية!
Very well. Go there at once.
حسناً. اذهب إلى هناك فوراً.
[He]
[هو]
Yan Zheng!
يان تشنغ!
I knew you would come.
كنت أعلم أنك ستأتي.
Stay behind me. Keep close.
ابقَ خلفي. ابقَ قريباً.
I won't hide behind anyone.
لن أختبئ وراء أحد.
Lord Changxin or Sui Yuanqing? Pick one.
اللورد تشانغشين أو سوي يوانكينغ؟ اختر واحدة.
Lord Changxin.
اللورد تشانغشين.
Be careful.
احرص.
Hyah!
هيا!
[He]
[هو]
[Sui]
[على]
Brother!
أخ!
Then you can die with him!
ثم يمكنك أن تموت معه!
Mandi!
استحم!
Sui Yuanqing! I'll kill you!
سوي يوانكينغ! سأقتلك!
Brother!
أخ!
Mandi!
استحم!
-Mandi!
-استحم!
Yuanqing!
يوانكينج!
Lead the troops to attack the city, now!
قُد القوات لمهاجمة المدينة، الآن!
Mandi!
استحم!
Xie brat!
شي برات!
Do you really think you can win?
هل تعتقد حقاً أنك تستطيع الفوز؟
Look at the smoke signals behind me.
انظر إلى إشارات الدخان خلفي.
The Chongzhou Army has already breached Lucheng!
لقد تمكن جيش تشونغتشو بالفعل من اختراق لوتشنغ!
You can't go anywhere today!
لا يمكنك الذهاب إلى أي مكان اليوم!
Xie Wu!
شكرًا لك!
Stay here and protect Changyu!
ابقَ هنا واحمِ تشانغيو!
Yes!
نعم!
Hyah!
هيا!
Where are you running, Xie brat?
إلى أين تهربين يا شيه الصغيرة؟
How strange.
يا للعجب!
How dare a pawn like you stop me?
كيف يجرؤ بيدق مثلك على إيقافي؟
To kill a rebellious old man like you,
لقتل رجل عجوز متمرد مثلك،
I can do it alone!
أستطيع فعل ذلك بمفردي!
Arrogant brat.
طفل متغطرس.
When I was leading armies to kill enemies,
عندما كنت أقود الجيوش لقتل الأعداء،
you were still a kid.
كنت لا تزال طفلاً.
Not bad, kid.
ليس سيئاً يا فتى.
Following that Xie brat is a waste of your talent.
بعد ذلك، فإنّ إنجاب طفل صغير من شيه هو إهدار لموهبتك.
Why not follow me from now on?
لماذا لا تتابعني من الآن فصاعدًا؟
I am a Xie for life.
أنا من عائلة شي مدى الحياة.
I will never take a dog's last name!
لن أتخذ اسم عائلة كلب أبداً!
You don't know what's good for you.
أنت لا تعرف ما هو الأفضل لك.
You're good with short blades,
أنت تجيد استخدام الشفرات القصيرة،
but your moves are heavy and powerful.
لكن تحركاتك قوية وفعّالة.
Use less brute force,
استخدم قوة أقل،
go with the flow,
اتبع التيار،
and use more finesse
واستخدم المزيد من البراعة
On the battlefield,
في ساحة المعركة،
the enemy's moves change in an instant.
تتغير تحركات العدو في لحظة.
How can you lose your composure
كيف يمكن أن تفقد رباطة جأشك؟
the moment someone sees through your move?
ماذا سيحدث عندما يكتشف أحدهم خطتك؟
You think you can defeat me with these petty tricks?
أتظن أنك تستطيع هزيمتي بهذه الحيل التافهة؟
Kill me.
اقتلني.
Make it quick!
أسرع!
Tie him up. Take him back.
اربطه. أعده.
Yes!
نعم!
♪ The world is vast ♪
♪ العالم واسع ♪
♪ The storm is rising ♪
♪ العاصفة تتصاعد ♪
Who is He Jingyuan to you?
من هو هي جينغ يوان بالنسبة لك؟
He is the commander of our Jizhou Army.
هو قائد جيش جيتشو التابع لنا.
This blade technique of yours
تقنية الشفرة هذه التي تستخدمها
♪ Day and night ♪
♪ ليلاً ونهاراً ♪
was created by the Two Tiger Generals of the Wei Family.
تم إنشاؤها بواسطة الجنرالين النمرين من عائلة وي.
But Wei Qilin is dead.
لكن وي تشيلين مات.
♪ We strive to save the world ♪
♪ نسعى جاهدين لإنقاذ العالم ♪
Only He Jingyuan still knows this technique.
لا يزال هي جينغ يوان وحده يعرف هذه التقنية.
How did you learn it from him?
كيف تعلمت ذلك منه؟
You know General He's sworn brother?
هل تعرف الجنرال؟ إنه أخٌ مُقسِم؟
The big traitor Wei Qilin?
الخائن الكبير وي تشيلين؟
♪ All people ♪
♪ جميع الناس ♪
Who doesn't know him?
من لا يعرفه؟
Who hasn't heard of him?
من منا لم يسمع به؟
♪ Are part of the past ♪
♪ جزء من الماضي ♪
♪ What's the date today? ♪
♪ ما هو تاريخ اليوم؟ ♪
Once I have captured you,
بمجرد أن أقبض عليك،
♪ How lamentable ♪
♪ يا للأسف ♪
while He Jingyuan is still barely alive,
بينما لا يزال هي جينغ يوان على قيد الحياة بالكاد،
I'll negotiate another deal with him!
سأتفاوض معه على صفقة أخرى!
♪ The world is vast ♪
♪ العالم واسع ♪
♪ The storm is rising ♪
♪ العاصفة تتصاعد ♪
♪ Day and night ♪
♪ ليلاً ونهاراً ♪
♪ We strive to save the world ♪
♪ نسعى جاهدين لإنقاذ العالم ♪
Please send troops to rescue them immediately!
أرجو إرسال قوات لإنقاذهم على الفور!
♪ All people ♪
♪ جميع الناس ♪
♪ Are part of the past ♪
♪ جزء من الماضي ♪
♪ What's the date today? ♪
♪ ما هو تاريخ اليوم؟ ♪
♪ How lamentable ♪
♪ يا للأسف ♪
[Sui]
[على]
[Jizhou Government Office]
[مكتب حكومة جيتشو]
How did a fine young lady...
كيف فعلت ذلك سيدة شابة رائعة...
get hurt like this?
هل يمكن أن أتعرض للأذى بهذه الطريقة؟
I didn't mean to hide my identity.
لم أكن أنوي إخفاء هويتي.
Are you...
أنت...
angry?
غاضب؟
Back in the military camp,
بالعودة إلى المعسكر العسكري،
I knew you were not just anybody.
كنت أعرف أنك لست أي شخص.
But I never expected
لكنني لم أتوقع ذلك أبداً
that you were the noble Princess Royal.
أنكِ كنتِ الأميرة الملكية النبيلة.
And now you're treating my injury.
والآن أنت تعالج إصابتي.
I also thought my status was noble,
كنت أعتقد أيضاً أن مكانتي نبيلة،
and that agreeing to a marriage alliance for the country
والموافقة على تحالف زواج للبلاد
would be the greatest sacrifice of my life.
سيكون ذلك أعظم تضحية في حياتي.
But after going to the battlefield, I realized
لكن بعد ذهابي إلى ساحة المعركة، أدركت
being a Princess Royal means nothing.
لا يعني كونك أميرة ملكية شيئاً.
Now, beheading the rebel leader
والآن، قطع رأس زعيم المتمردين
is a glory you earned with your own hands.
إنه مجدٌ نلته بيديك.
Now that Lord Changxin is dead,
والآن بعد وفاة اللورد تشانغشين،
the court and the public will be shaken.
ستهتز المحكمة والجمهور.
Your name will be remembered by everyone in Great Yin
سيتذكر الجميع في يين العظمى اسمك
and recorded in history.
ومسجلة في التاريخ.
I'm bowing to you
أنا أنحني لك
as the Princess Royal,
بصفتها الأميرة الملكية،
and also as Qi Shu.
وأيضًا باسم تشي شو.
Changyu, have a good rest.
تشانغيو، أتمنى لك راحة جيدة.
I used to think...
كنت أعتقد...
that as long as I was kind,
طالما كنتُ لطيفاً،
I could protect those around me.
كان بإمكاني حماية من حولي.
But after experiencing life and death separations, I realized...
لكن بعد أن عشت تجربة الفراق بين الحياة والموت، أدركت...
misplaced kindness
لطف في غير محله
will only drive more people to desperation.
لن يؤدي ذلك إلا إلى دفع المزيد من الناس إلى اليأس.
Sister...
أخت...
I'm here.
أنا هنا.
Brother...
أخ...
Look how well I've done.
انظروا إلى مدى نجاحي.
I... I'm not a coward.
أنا... أنا لست جباناً.
Mandi!
استحم!
Godfather was right.
كان العراب محقاً.
On the battlefield,
في ساحة المعركة،
it's either you die or your opponent does.
إما أن تموت أنت أو يموت خصمك.
Where is General He?
أين الجنرال هي؟
General He... is on the city walls.
الجنرال هي... موجود على أسوار المدينة.
Hurry!
عجل!
General, we won!
يا جنرال، لقد انتصرنا!
[He]
[هو]
General?
عام؟
General!
عام!
If I had known this...
لو كنت أعرف هذا...
if I had killed Lord Changxin sooner,
لو كنت قتلت اللورد تشانغشين في وقت أبكر،
General He and the others wouldn't have...
الجنرال هي والآخرون ما كانوا ليفعلوا ذلك...
General He's death
الجنرال هي الموت
is not your fault.
ليس خطأك.
Changyu,
تشانغيو،
he was just like you—
كان مثلك تماماً—
wanting to protect this land.
الرغبة في حماية هذه الأرض.
Your Highness, Mrs. Fan, Lord Li is requesting a meeting.
صاحبة السمو، السيدة فان، يطلب اللورد لي عقد اجتماع.
Let him in.
دعه يدخل.
Changyu,
تشانغيو،
take a good rest.
خذ قسطاً جيداً من الراحة.
I'm off now.
سأغادر الآن.
Captain Li.
الكابتن لي.
You all have earned merit.
لقد استحققتم جميعاً الجدارة.
Recover well.
أتمنى لك الشفاء العاجل.
Lord Li.
اللورد لي.
Commandant Fan, you played the hero
أيها القائد فان، لقد لعبت دور البطل
and finally got what you wanted.
وأخيراً حصلت على ما تريد.
You were injured too badly.
لقد تعرضت لإصابة بالغة.
Knocking you out
سأطرحك أرضاً
was to stop you from acting rashly
كان الهدف هو منعك من التصرف بتهور.
and throwing your life away.
وإضاعة حياتك.
I would rather have died outside the city
كنت أفضل الموت خارج المدينة
than be knocked out,
بدلاً من أن يُغمى عليه،
only to wake up and be told the battle is over.
ثم يستيقظ المرء ليُقال له إن المعركة قد انتهت.
It's even impossible for me
بل إنه أمر مستحيل بالنسبة لي
to avenge my master.
لأنتقم لسيدي.
I'm just a joke now.
أنا مجرد نكتة الآن.
It would be a real joke
سيكون ذلك مزحة حقيقية
if Lord He's prized disciple were to die foolishly
لو مات تلميذ الرب هي المفضل ميتة حماقة
in a moment of anger.
في لحظة غضب.
I came here
لقد أتيت إلى هنا
to fulfill Master's dying wish.
لتحقيق أمنية السيد الأخيرة.
[To He]
[إلى هو]
Let's not meet again.
دعونا لا نلتقي مرة أخرى.
He...
هو...
[Thanks to your help, He,]
[بفضل مساعدتك يا هو]
Help...
يساعد...
In shame... 100,000...
عارٌ... 100,000...
[Now the Prime Minister has issued another kill order.]
[والآن أصدر رئيس الوزراء أمراً آخر بالقتل.]
Thanks to your help, He,
بفضل مساعدتك يا هو،
I have lived until now in shame.
لقد عشت حتى الآن في عار.
I wish to restore the truth to the 100,000 souls of Jinzhou.
أرغب في إعادة الحقيقة إلى أرواح المئة ألف نسمة في جينتشو.
Now the Prime Minister has issued another kill order.
والآن أصدر رئيس الوزراء أمراً آخر بالقتل.
Blabla... can no longer live in shame.
كلام فارغ... لم يعد بإمكاني العيش في خجل.
Nor do I wish to put you in a difficult position.
ولا أرغب في وضعك في موقف صعب.
I, Qilin, can no longer live in shame.
أنا، كيلين، لم أعد أستطيع العيش في خزي.
Nor do I wish to put you in a difficult position.
ولا أرغب في وضعك في موقف صعب.
I will end my life along with my wife.
سأنهي حياتي مع زوجتي.
[I, Qilin, can no longer live in shame.]
[أنا، كيلين، لم أعد أستطيع العيش في خزي.]
Our lives
حياتنا
have lasted 16 extra years.
لقد استمرت 16 سنة إضافية.
[I, Qilin, can no longer live in shame.]
[أنا، كيلين، لم أعد أستطيع العيش في خزي.]
It has been a great fortune.
لقد كان ذلك حظاً عظيماً.
I beg you, He,
أرجوك يا هو،
to protect
للحماية
my two daughters.
ابنتيّ الاثنتين.
Sister.
أخت.
Sister?
أخت؟
Coward,
جبان،
pretend you never saw this letter today.
تظاهر بأنك لم ترَ هذه الرسالة اليوم.
And don't tell anyone else about this.
ولا تخبر أحداً آخر بهذا الأمر.
Leave the letter here. Go back now.
اترك الرسالة هنا. ارجع الآن.
Alright, Sister.
حسناً يا أختي.
You know General He's sworn brother?
هل تعرف الجنرال؟ إنه أخٌ مُقسِم؟
The big traitor Wei Qilin?
الخائن الكبير وي تشيلين؟
Who doesn't know him?
من لا يعرفه؟
Who hasn't heard of him?
من منا لم يسمع به؟
The big traitor, Wei Qilin.
الخائن الكبير، وي تشيلين.
He escorted the grain with no loyalty
رافق الحبوب دون أي ولاء
[Wei Qilin]
[وي تشيلين]
and cost 100,000 heroes their lives!
وكلّف ذلك 100 ألف بطل حياتهم!
My father was Wei...
كان والدي وي...
Wei Qilin?
وي تشيلين؟
The big traitor Wei Qilin?
الخائن الكبير وي تشيلين؟
That can't be true.
لا يمكن أن يكون ذلك صحيحاً.
That can't be true. That can't be true.
لا يمكن أن يكون هذا صحيحاً. لا يمكن أن يكون هذا صحيحاً.
If my father were a traitor who harmed the country and the people,
لو كان والدي خائناً ألحق الضرر بالبلاد والشعب،
with my mother's temper,
بسبب طبع أمي الحاد،
how could she ever forgive him?
كيف لها أن تسامحه؟
But what exactly happened?
لكن ما الذي حدث بالضبط؟
Crown Prince Chengde and General Xie Linshan
ولي العهد تشنغده والجنرال شيه لينشان
defended the border,
دافعوا عن الحدود،
fighting valiantly on the battlefield.
يقاتلون ببسالة في ساحة المعركة.
The big traitor Wei Qilin colluded with Beijue,
الخائن الكبير وي تشيلين تواطأ مع بيجوي،
delaying the army's provisions.
تأخير إمدادات الجيش.
One hundred thousand soldiers
مئة ألف جندي
starved for 5 days and nights.
تضورنا جوعاً لمدة خمسة أيام وليالٍ.
The big traitor Wei Qilin.
الخائن الكبير هو وي تشيلين.
Who doesn't know him?
من لا يعرفه؟
[Wei Qilin]
[وي تشيلين]
Who hasn't heard of him?
من منا لم يسمع به؟
The big traitor, Wei Qilin.
الخائن الكبير، وي تشيلين.
[Wei Qilin]
[وي تشيلين]
He escorted the grain with no loyalty
رافق الحبوب دون أي ولاء
and cost 100,000 heroes their lives!
وكلّف ذلك 100 ألف بطل حياتهم!
Jinzhou was suffering, the soldiers seethed.
كانت جينتشو تعاني، وكان الجنود يغلي غضباً.
He caused the Crown Prince's death and the people to starve to death.
تسبب في وفاة ولي العهد وموت الشعب جوعاً.
General...
عام...
Fan Changyu!
فان تشانغيو!
Stop singing!
توقف عن الغناء!
Come here!
تعال الى هنا!
Do you understand why you're kneeling?
هل تفهم لماذا تركع؟
Mother,
الأم،
I won't play the "Big Traitor" game anymore.
لن ألعب لعبة "الخائن الكبير" بعد الآن.
Good girl, Changyu.
فتاة جيدة يا تشانغيو.
How many in this world
كم عددهم في هذا العالم؟
can truly distinguish
يمكن التمييز حقًا
loyalty from treachery and right from wrong?
الولاء من الخيانة والحق من الباطل؟
The big traitor, Wei Qilin.
الخائن الكبير، وي تشيلين.
No.
لا.
My father was not him.
لم يكن والدي هو هو.
It's not true.
هذا غير صحيح.
It's not true!
هذا غير صحيح!
It's me.
هذا أنا.
Does it hurt?
هل يؤلمك؟
Is Sui Yuanqing...
هل سوي يوانكينغ...
dead?
ميت؟
He escaped.
لقد هرب.
Your Highness, I've come to save you!
يا صاحب السمو، لقد جئت لإنقاذك!
Take the Heir Apparent away now!
اسحبوا ولي العهد الآن!
Hyah!
هيا!
Let's go!
دعنا نذهب!
He will die sooner or later.
سيموت عاجلاً أم آجلاً.
I will bring his head back to Lin'an
سأعيد رأسه إلى لينآن
to pay tribute to our people.
تكريماً لشعبنا.
Alright.
على ما يرام.
It must hurt, right?
لا بد أن الأمر مؤلم، أليس كذلك؟
It's just a minor cut.
إنه مجرد جرح بسيط.
How is General Wu's injury?
كيف حال إصابة الجنرال وو؟
He broke his shoulder.
لقد كسر كتفه.
Fortunately, he's always been strong.
لحسن الحظ، كان دائماً قوياً.
His life is not in danger.
حياته ليست في خطر.
(Watch on www.dramacool.club Support Admin)
(شاهد على www.dramacool.club دعم الإدارة)
It's just that...
الأمر فقط هو...
he may not be able to wield a sword again.
قد لا يتمكن من حمل السيف مرة أخرى.
It was all to protect me.
كان كل ذلك لحمايتي.
He risked his life twice on the battlefield to save me.
لقد خاطر بحياته مرتين في ساحة المعركة لإنقاذي.
I owe him a lot.
أنا مدين له بالكثير.
Today,
اليوم،
if he hadn't blocked that spear from Lord Changxin,
لو لم يصدّ تلك الرمح عن اللورد تشانغشين،
I would have died.
كنت سأموت.
In this world,
في هذا العالم،
No one has the right to make you die.
لا يحق لأحد أن يتسبب في موتك.
I've been having nightmares all night.
لقد كنت أعاني من الكوابيس طوال الليل.
In them, it was either Mandi's face
في تلك الصور، كان وجه ماندي إما
or the faces of our soldiers.
أو وجوه جنودنا.
They died over and over again in my dreams.
كانوا يموتون مراراً وتكراراً في أحلامي.
And every time,
وفي كل مرة،
every time, I couldn't save them.
في كل مرة، لم أستطع إنقاذهم.
Was the Battle of Jinzhou 17 years ago
هل وقعت معركة جينتشو قبل 17 عامًا؟
just as brutal?
بنفس القدر من الوحشية؟
The Battle of Jinzhou
معركة جينتشو
was even worse.
بل كان الأمر أسوأ.
Seventeen years ago,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً،
my father fought the Beijue Army for months.
حارب والدي جيش بيجوي لشهور.
But because supplies never arrived
لكن لأن الإمدادات لم تصل أبداً
and reinforcements didn't come,
ولم تصل التعزيزات،
the soldiers were too weak to resist, and the city fell.
كان الجنود أضعف من أن يقاوموا، فسقطت المدينة.
Beijue people marched straight in.
سار شعب بيجوي مباشرة إلى الداخل.
Tens of thousands of lives were treated as worthless as grass.
تم التعامل مع عشرات الآلاف من الأرواح على أنها لا قيمة لها مثل العشب.
And my father was hanged on the city wall.
وأُعدم والدي شنقاً على سور المدينة.
Then,
ثم،
the one who transported the grain back then...
الشخص الذي كان ينقل الحبوب آنذاك...
Wei Qilin...
وي تشيلين...
Did he really...
هل فعل ذلك حقاً...
cause so many people to die?
تسبب في موت الكثير من الناس؟
Is it possible there's another story?
هل من الممكن أن تكون هناك قصة أخرى؟
Wei Qilin
وي تشيلين
was Wei Yan's most trusted general back then.
كان الجنرال الأكثر ثقة لدى وي يان آنذاك.
He also fought side by side with my father.
كما أنه قاتل جنباً إلى جنب مع والدي.
He was a loyal and righteous man.
كان رجلاً مخلصاً وصالحاً.
But later,
لكن لاحقاً،
in the eyes of the Yanzhou Army,
في نظر جيش يانتشو،
he became a traitor to Great Yin.
لقد أصبح خائناً لـ"غريت يين".
Why do you suddenly ask about this?
لماذا تسأل عن هذا فجأة؟
Fan Changyu, tell him.
يا فان تشانغيو، أخبره.
Telling him the truth is the right thing to do.
إن إخباره بالحقيقة هو الشيء الصحيح الذي يجب فعله.
Even if he turns against you from now on,
حتى لو انقلب عليك من الآن فصاعدًا،
it would just be the right thing to do.
سيكون هذا هو الشيء الصحيح الذي يجب فعله.
Tell him!
أخبره!
Changyu?
تشانغيو؟
I want to know,
أريد أن أعرف،
when will General He's funeral be held?
متى ستقام جنازة الجنرال هي؟
In 6 days.
خلال 6 أيام.
General He's seventh-day memorial coincides with my father's memorial ceremony.
يتزامن اليوم السابع لإحياء ذكرى الجنرال هي مع مراسم إحياء ذكرى والدي.
It's almost like it was destined.
يبدو الأمر وكأنه كان مقدراً.
Seventeen years ago today,
قبل سبعة عشر عاماً من اليوم،
my father died in battle in Jinzhou.
توفي والدي في معركة في جينتشو.
Every year at this time,
في مثل هذا الوقت من كل عام،
the generals of the Xie family,
جنرالات عائلة شي،
no matter where they are,
بغض النظر عن مكان وجودهم،
return to pay their respects to my father.
يعودون لتقديم واجب العزاء لوالدي.
Then at that time,
ثم في ذلك الوقت،
I also want to offer incense for General Xie.
أرغب أيضاً في تقديم البخور للجنرال شيه.
May I?
ربما أنا؟
Yes.
نعم.
[The Coffin of He Jingyuan, General of Loyalty of Great Yin]
[تابوت هي جينغ يوان، قائد ولاء يين العظيم]
[In Memory of My Late Father, Xie Linshan]
[في ذكرى والدي الراحل، شي لينشان]
Wenkan,
شكرًا لك،
since you were a child,
منذ أن كنت طفلاً،
you've been following me.
لقد كنت تتابعني.
You are my proudest student.
أنت أكثر طلابي فخراً.
The reason I kept you by my side
السبب الذي جعلني أبقيك بجانبي
is that the court is treacherous and unpredictable.
إن المحكمة غادرة ولا يمكن التنبؤ بتصرفاتها.
The Li and Wei factions manipulate power.
تتلاعب فصائل لي ووي بالسلطة.
I don't want you to be misled by them
لا أريد أن تضللك هذه الأمور
and become a pawn in their schemes.
ويصبحون مجرد بيدق في مخططاتهم.
What I hope for
ما أتمناه
is that you become a loyal subject of Great Yin.
هو أن تصبح تابعًا مخلصًا لـ"الين العظيم".
There is one more thing.
هناك شيء آخر.
It concerns the Fan sisters.
الأمر يتعلق بالأخوات فان.
After I am gone,
بعد رحيلي،
I hope you can treat them with sincerity.
أتمنى أن تعاملهم بصدق.
Only then can I rest in peace.
عندها فقط أستطيع أن أرتاح بسلام.
Lord Li, this is the elegiac couplet sent by Prime Minister Wei.
يا سيد لي، هذا هو البيت الشعري الرثائي الذي أرسله رئيس الوزراء وي.
[With iron will and a tempered blade, he chilled the enemy;]
[بإرادة حديدية وسيفه المصقول، أرعب العدو؛]
Lord Li,
اللورد لي،
[his loyal name shines like the sun, his spirit stands tall.]
[اسمه الوفي يسطع كالشمس، وروحه شامخة.]
this is the elegiac couplet sent by Grand Tutor Li.
هذا هو البيت الشعري الرثائي الذي أرسله المعلم الكبير لي.
His blood-forged soul shines in history; his righteous courage humbles us.
روحه التي صقلتها الدماء تتألق في التاريخ؛ وشجاعته النبيلة تجعلنا نشعر بالتواضع.
My Lord, which pair have you decided to hang?
يا سيدي، أي زوج قررت شنقه؟
This means you've decided to help the Grand Tutor against the Wei faction?
هذا يعني أنك قررت مساعدة المعلم الأكبر ضد فصيل واي؟
I, Huaian, will carry on your legacy,
أنا، هوايان، سأحمل إرثك،
and won't let down the soldiers and civilians
ولن يخذل الجنود والمدنيين
of Great Yin who sacrificed their lives.
من الين العظيم الذين ضحوا بحياتهم.
[Ximo Pavilion]
[جناح زيمو]
Cousin.
ابن عم.
Please enjoy.
استمتعوا.
[Liu Wan'er, the illegitimate daughter of a cousin of Lord Changxin's wife]
[ليو وان إير، الابنة غير الشرعية لابن عم زوجة اللورد تشانغشين]
Mother said...
قالت الأم...
your injuries are severe.
إصاباتك خطيرة.
This tonic is good for...
هذا المنشط مفيد لـ...
healing wounds.
التئام الجروح.
She also said...
وقالت أيضاً...
that Father has already found out
لقد اكتشف الأب ذلك بالفعل
the Marquis of Wu'an isn't paying attention to this place.
لا يولي ماركيز ووآن أي اهتمام لهذا المكان.
So please, stay here...
لذا من فضلك، ابقَ هنا...
and recover in peace.
وتعافى بسلام.
Why are you shaking so badly?
لماذا ترتجف بشدة؟
Are you afraid of me?
هل أنت خائف مني؟
Cousin!
ابن عم!
Careful. It's hot.
انتبه. الجو حار.
I don't like plain food.
أنا لا أحب الطعام البسيط.
Why don't you...
لماذا لا تفعل ذلك...
drink it for me?
اشربها نيابة عني؟
I...
أنا...
Cousin!
ابن عم!
Run.
يجري.
Father heard that the Marquis of Wu'an is coming to arrest you personally
سمع أبي أن ماركيز ووآن قادم لاعتقالك شخصياً
and is afraid that our whole family will be executed if the city falls.
ويخشى أن يتم إعدام عائلتنا بأكملها إذا سقطت المدينة.
He put poison in the soup,
وضع السم في الحساء،
saying he would offer your head to surrender.
قال إنه سيعرض رأسك مقابل الاستسلام.
I'm so sorry.
أنا آسف جدا.
I didn't want to hurt you.
لم أكن أريد أن أؤذيك.
Thanks for telling me, Cousin.
شكراً لإخبارك لي يا ابن عمي.
[Ximo Pavilion]
[جناح زيمو]
Father!
أب!
Mother!
الأم!
Why did you kill my parents?
لماذا قتلت والديّ؟
With your skills,
بفضل مهاراتك،
you could have escaped!
كان بإمكانك الهرب!
Why didn't you just run?
لماذا لم تهرب فحسب؟
Why did you have to kill them?
لماذا كان عليك قتلهم؟
They were going to offer my head to surrender.
كانوا سيقدمون رأسي مقابل الاستسلام.
Why couldn't I kill them?
لماذا لم أستطع قتلهم؟
They aren't worth your tears.
إنهم لا يستحقون دموعك.
You don't mean that much to them.
أنت لا تعني لهم الكثير.
Otherwise,
خلاف ذلك،
they wouldn't have sent you to bring me that poisoned soup.
ما كانوا ليرسلوك لتحضر لي ذلك الحساء المسموم.
Now,
الآن،
you are free.
أنت حر.
Cousin, take me with you.
يا ابن عمي، خذني معك.
My family is dead.
لقد ماتت عائلتي.
I don't know where to go.
لا أعرف إلى أين أذهب.
I killed your whole family,
لقد قتلت عائلتك بأكملها،
and you still want to follow me?
وما زلت ترغب في متابعتي؟
I'm begging you.
أتوسل إليك.
Please take me with you.
أرجوك خذني معك.
What a delicate flower.
يا لها من زهرة رقيقة.
But why are some flowers, like you,
لكن لماذا بعض الزهور، مثلك،
only able to cling to and depend on others?
هل أنت قادر فقط على التشبث بالآخرين والاعتماد عليهم؟
Without others,
بدون الآخرين،
you can't survive for a moment.
لا يمكنك البقاء على قيد الحياة ولو للحظة.
And some flowers
وبعض الزهور
grow wild and free,
تنمو برية وحرة،
are covered in thorns,
مغطاة بالأشواك،
and make you love and hate them at the same time.
ويجعلك تحبهم وتكرههم في نفس الوقت.
Master, the Heir Apparent slaughtered the entire Liu family last night.
يا سيدي، لقد قام ولي العهد بذبح عائلة ليو بأكملها الليلة الماضية.
Big deal.
أمرٌ عظيم.
It's nothing to be surprised about.
لا داعي للدهشة.
Where is he?
أين هو؟
In the study.
في الدراسة.
Yuanqing!
يوانكينج!
Min!
مين!
I've finally found you.
لقد وجدتك أخيراً.
How are you?
كيف حالك؟
Is Mother alright?
هل الأم بخير؟
Min,
مين،
am I really...
هل أنا حقاً...
really inferior to Xie Zheng?
هل هو حقاً أقل شأناً من شيه تشنغ؟
Is that why I keep losing
هل هذا هو سبب خسارتي المستمرة؟
and caused Father's death?
وتسبب في وفاة الأب؟
To me,
لي،
you are the most formidable man in this world.
أنت الرجل الأكثر هيبة في هذا العالم.
Xie Zheng only won a few battles by sheer luck.
لم يفز شيه تشنغ إلا في عدد قليل من المعارك بفضل الحظ المحض.
But our great cause is not lost.
لكن قضيتنا العظيمة لم تضيع.
We still have a chance.
لا تزال لدينا فرصة.
Our great cause?
قضيتنا العظيمة؟
It's nothing but an illusion.
إنه ليس سوى وهم.
Ever since Father was misled by the Late Emperor,
منذ أن ضُلِّل والدي من قِبَل الإمبراطور الراحل،
he was obsessed with achieving this so-called great cause.
كان مهووساً بتحقيق هذه القضية العظيمة المزعومة.
And in the end?
وفي النهاية؟
It was all for nothing.
كان كل ذلك بلا جدوى.
I don't believe in this bullshit cause.
أنا لا أؤمن بهذه القضية السخيفة.
What do I care who becomes the Emperor?
ما يهمني من سيصبح الإمبراطور؟
The Sui family
عائلة سوي
cannot give up so easily!
لا يمكن الاستسلام بهذه السهولة!
Just because Xie Zheng has every advantage,
لمجرد أن شيه تشنغ يمتلك كل المزايا،
you're afraid to seek revenge?
هل تخشى الانتقام؟
Even though I am in poor health,
على الرغم من أنني أعاني من سوء الحالة الصحية،
I will use every last bit of strength in this broken body
سأستخدم كل ما تبقى لدي من قوة في هذا الجسد المنهك
to fight them to the death!
أن نقاتلهم حتى الموت!
What about you?
ماذا عنك؟
A true man stands tall between Heaven and Earth.
الرجل الحقيقي يقف شامخاً بين السماء والأرض.
How can you accept defeat without a fight?
كيف يمكنك قبول الهزيمة دون قتال؟
If we cannot win,
إذا لم نتمكن من الفوز،
that is our fate!
هذا هو مصيرنا!
Look at you today.
انظر إلى حالك اليوم.
You're a complete mess!
أنت في حالة فوضى عارمة!
How can you face Father's spirit in Heaven?
كيف يمكنك مواجهة روح الآب في السماء؟
Do you know who killed Father?
هل تعرف من قتل أبي؟
It wasn't Xie Zheng?
ألم يكن شيه تشنغ؟
It was Fan Changyu.
كان فان تشانغيو.
Fan Changyu?
فان تشانغيو؟
Fan Changyu!
فان تشانغيو!
She again?
هي مرة أخرى؟
That butcher girl again?
تلك الفتاة الجزارة مرة أخرى؟
How dare she!
يا لها من وقاحة!
Min!
مين!
I want revenge!
أريد الانتقام!
Go ahead.
تفضل.
No matter what you do,
مهما فعلت،
I will support you.
سأدعمك.
I will take care of Mother along the way.
سأعتني بأمي طوال الطريق.
Just go and kill Fan Changyu
اذهب واقتل فان تشانغيو
to appease Father's spirit in Heaven.
لإرضاء روح الآب في السماء.